hello I'm your host David Barnard and my
guest today is dilip ready a data
engineer turned marketer working on an
Apple search ads platform called search
ads
optimization on the podcast I talked
with dilip about the impact of Apple
search ads on organic search how to save
money on brand defense and why Ras
shouldn't be the only thing you optimize
for hey dilip thanks so much for joining
me on the podcast today yeah I'm excited
to be here talking about about Apple
searchs yeah I I've been meaning to do
an episode on Apple searchs for a long
time and you know there's so many
different frames of reference to talk
about it and so there's a few people
I've talked to that that I probably will
still have on but a little more like
kind of like growth hacky more kind of
marketer focused but one of the things
I'm excited to talk to you about search
ads is that you're a data guy and you
kind of like stumbled into marketing as
a data guy so let let's just kick it off
with that story like how did you get
into Apple search ads as a data
scientist the reason is I did computer
science and like um always uh data is my
go to like that's what fascinates me and
I started Bank of America there's no
like app thing and all um but over time
like I joined like um unicor app
companies like in
2016 and that's when the Apple sear came
in um it's a because I'm a data pi as
well so I manage all data sources and um
design architectures I noticed Apple s
is different in a way that it gives like
so many data points so much of data that
extreme granular including High intent
keywords how they uses so reacting and
it just was great and also I created my
own hobby apps that don't solve any real
problem but I started tinkering with
apple set chats and in a weird way
that's kind of my on and off I've been
like developing algorithms and all this
stuff and that's how I ended up and yeah
yeah and then you you told me at one
point that uh one of the things that
really fascinated you about Apple search
ads was that you were digging through
the data one time and saw some like
really high bids and some high cost for
acquisition um yeah so tell me about
that yeah I mean there are some
categories right like Finance health and
fitness um the bits are like can be like
go crazy for some Market some keywords
but they also bring in higher Revenue um
that's what is interesting because if
you look at in a spray and prey networks
like meta everything is usually like
constant you expect this and like the
same Revenue performance because this
not intent based it's just shooting
creative across millions and hoping some
will fall for it but Apple switch has
the even the CPS is high I find it like
you know there's something we can Tinker
with and like experiment with uh because
we cannot stop just because it's high
CPA because they're the high intent and
in a way it's a limited inventory demand
and Supply so it depends on the app it
depends on what keywords we're targeting
and what kind of users we're looking for
and especially for very high competitive
like Finance is one thing health and
fitness yeah we may see bits go really
high up and CPA can go high in USA USA
is one of the most expensive storefront
yeah and that's the interesting thing
about search ads I mean it's why Google
is a what trillion plus dollar company
it's said when when people go search for
a specific term they're they're very
clearly demonstrating intent and you
know I don't remember all the different
categories but there there's things like
you know searching for divorce lawyer on
Google whereas like the bids are just
seem insane but if you're searching
divorce lawyer you know some something
something's going on in your life life
and it's a lot of you know the lawyers
make a lot of money on divorce
settlements and so it's like they can
bid really high and I think there's kind
of similar market dynamics at play in
the App Store where for things like
finance and health and fitness where
there's High intent there's High
willingness to pay it makes sense in
kind of a competitive bid environment
that some of the keywords will get bit
up and it's kind of cool that like what
part of what got you into Apple search
ads was seeing those High bids and be
like wait a minute this data must be
wrong but no it's like actually the data
was correct it's just that you can have
a return on ad spend with like a $50 CPA
if it's the right keyword and the right
app and the right monetization um so
that's really interesting yeah and yeah
the good thing about it is we can
control each and every aspect at gr new
L work I mean you can also like stop
some keywords like bid really low so
either forcing Apple to stop giving us
Impressions or give more installs for
the same uh not more installs but
similar installs uh with a lesser CPA
that's the best part we can we are in
control of everything it's not like meta
right like we don't know why the CP is
going high and I can't do anything about
it yeah a lot of granular control and a
lot of data to to understand what's
going on yeah it is a double HED SW it
can get overwhelming especially if a
company is running in know all 60
countries and 70 countries like
thousands of keywords for each country I
mean we have some solution for that and
there's some kind of Campa structure you
can set up to make it the mental
Overlord much better I I want to kind of
kick things off talking about trends for
2024 I mean things are always changing
you know Apple introduced the brand or
not I guess not brand but like the
inventory on on search and they've kind
of been expanding inventory over the
last few years anything especially
interesting in 2024 that that that it's
changing in app store search ads that
folks should be paying attention to a
lot of apps now usually it used to be
like we just run in tier one like you
know us UK like Germany France and
forget the rest of the world but now I'm
noticing the trend of adding as many as
countries as possible because if you
think about it there's only like five
six localizations that we have to like
for example if there's a Spanish um you
can maybe have an entire Latin America
not entire but most of the Latin America
with the same kind of keywords same with
Portuguese German or France the way is
like we identify the keyword Builder
building for these
localizations but you can expand to
pretty much every country in the world
and for extreme
local language that we cannot support
our Apple defaults to English anyway so
expanding to more countries is what I'm
noticing and and apple introduced new um
geographies this year right yeah yeah
Brazil um and I think six other Latin
count so yeah this the best way and
people are seeing some surprising
results so my advice is test these
countries because we can just assume oh
because this country is this we should
not run it there especially the effort
is pretty much same it takes maybe few
minutes to just copy and paste the
campaigns right yeah but you don't want
to just copy and paste the campaigns
right you want to copy and paste and
then spend a little time kind of honing
it in for that market and then you know
check your CPAs and your return on ad
spend and stuff like that yeah whenever
there's a new St friend my go to is
start with bids like too stupidly low
that will never get impressions but
that's fine we can always increase it if
you start bits high for a new country we
don't know what is the base I can start
with $10 Apple happily give me $10 bits
but maybe I can get the same number of
installs or 90% of installs if I bid
half right so and also the trend is I'm
noticing is the CP is going a bit high
and I'm assuming it's also across all ad
channels U because I don't deal with
other AD channels but the data suggest
CPS are going a bit High year by year so
we're dealing with that so yeah it kind
of makes sense because as apps get more
sophisticated about monetization and
really get their monetization dialed in
then they can spend more and so like the
market dynamics is like add as consumers
get more comfortable spending as
inflation causes higher prices to make
more sense you know as apps work on
their funnels and pay walls and all the
things like we talk about on the podcast
is like we're kind of creating the
problem like as more apps get more
sophisticated then they can bid higher
because they're going to still get a
return on ad spin even with that higher
CPA so it kind of makes sense that
there's just like kind of rising uh CPAs
especially with the most high intent um
search ads yeah I think there's also a
trend of I call these apps
hyperscalers it's like teu right like
they B 100,000 keywords for some reason
but the reason is maybe I don't know why
but they must have like billions of
marketing right so unfortunately it will
raise up it's like a a wave lifting up
all the boards kind of thing right so
because U is waiting for each and every
possible English character I'm English
letter and word Hindi the
it may mean that you know the CBA may be
going high I'm not saying this is the
reason exactly but this is a trend I'm
noticing as well yeah probably
contributes to it for sure yeah and
there's a new search inventory came in
that didn't exist before chpt is the AI
everything AI yoga AI right like uh
pretty much there's like entire new
generation of Search terms coming so the
inventory went up as well um so it's not
like all like high CPA for the same
inventory but also the apps like
Skyrocket a number of apps released
ironically a is making easier to create
much many apps at scale as well so yeah
that's the trends so far yeah yeah
that's really interesting and the
explosion of apps thing is interesting I
mean it does seem like AI has kind of
accelerated that is that you know like
you said for every for every major
category you might want to bid on
there's probably somebody who who is
either built like a more really
sophisticated app or rebranded an
existing app to like say it's a the AI
version of it and then you know people
are looking for more apps because
they're thinking well hey I've been
using this you know productivity to-do
list is there like a better AI version
of a to-do list that's going to make me
more productive and then they go back
and search whereas like maybe they
weren't searching some of those terms
before because they kind of had their
their the app that they used it would be
interesting to see the iOS new version
with the built-in AI how it's going to
impact a lot of apps um yeah let's see
how it goes with the AI so one of the
hotter topics I want to get your take on
is brand defense so you know you have
some people say never do brand defense
you're just like it's extortion from
Apple and Google to force you to do
brand defense on SEO and ASO but what
are your thoughts like can it work can
it be profitable how how should you
structure it if you do do it like how do
you think about brand defense on apps
shs yeah obviously it's a touchy subject
I have some opinions but what I would do
is like I asked I inquir company what is
your like like what is your plan like
what do you think of this because it
depends on each and every company on a
surface level this is what I would
suggest if your app is easily replaced
with a computor app you have to run
brand the unfortunate situation here is
that if you lose impression share that
we cannot measure that because it's a
lost opportunity we can only measure
something I mean incrementality but it's
a loss of um Revenue right if you think
about it let's say a company is running
Facebook Tik Tok um brand
awareness all that touch points made
that user come to the app store right
before downloading if a competitor solve
the exact same problem um it's a really
huge risk right like we made all the
hard work and now the competitors are
benefiting from it there are some apps
like with apps with network effects and
like uh we know these apps cannot be
replaced with on apps they do not need
to run you know brand um for example
maybe Bank of America app no one creates
online application but there's an
opportunity for like fintech apps right
uh because that's their opportunity Bank
of for doesn't need that but fintech can
capitalize on that opportunity
my suggestion is test with bidding lower
for the brand keywords you'll be
surprised you may be paying let's take
one example an app is getting 100%
impression share to be honest it's not
100 because there's never 100% imprison
share let's say 90% impression share is
there a way to measure that
incrementality testing or or is does
Apple actually like show you this
impression share this is a best part
Apple does give us impression share per
search term per country so so that is
one thing we can keep track of that this
reason why it allows us to conduct this
test is Bid lower for brand and test it
out and if you retain same impression
share you essentially have the cost um
still getting like same impression share
it is a test because we don't know how
impression share can take a hit and
maybe some companies are okay with 70%
impression share if it reduces cost by
70% so it's a nice trade-off he's still
retaining we still like letting go off
our impressions for other competitors
but we can use that budget for generic
High intent and these are actual new
users right and regarding Apple
extrating um I mean it's not unique to
Apple right like I mean it's every ad
Channel there's no trademark on search
DRS so yeah it's unfortunate reality of
everyone has to deal with but it's also
an opportunity right the impression
share is an interesting way to approach
it though because you're you're right
it's like if if you can spend half as
much money and get 90% impression share
versus twice as much money to get it to
100% that extra 10% is probably not
incrementally better than just spending
less and getting the 90% And then
something you and I were talking about
was how the the search ad algorithm does
tend to prefer the actual branded app
where you could potentially even bid a
lot lower than your competitors and
still win the bid because Apple's not
just going with the highest bid there is
some amount of like them trying to fit
the best app right yeah uh it's because
of one mechanism is that kosper tap
model um Apple only charges an app
company if someone Taps on it if you if
you get a million impressions with zero
Taps you basically got all this free 1
million impressions so if that's the
case right like if Apple just takes
highest bit like teu will be showing up
for a research ter but it's not the
reason is
imagine like if I'm a yoga app a famous
yoga app and someone is searching for
the yoga app of my
brand a competitor may not get same
level of Engagement a lot of users may
see the ad and oh you know what I I
don't care about it I heard about this
app so I'm going to download that apple
is losing too and it's also not great
user experience right like some if if
user is typing for yoga brand of XYZ
they're expecting to see XYZ not
So eventually Apple may like shift the
terms to Brand even if you're bidding
like let's say half of the computor
because it there's some
calculations it is also a test because
it's not guaranteed outcome imagine I'm
a just generic yoga app and the
competitor has better way better
screenshots way better messaging way
better ratings um I may lose that and
apple may think you know what this
computor appap is actually working
better more than this brand so Apple may
like give the impression share um so it
is a bit of test but yeah that's where
it's ideal to monitor the um impression
share and make sure we're not like
tanking yeah yeah that makes a lot of
sense because like yeah you're right
it's like in your example earlier I
think is maybe even better it's like if
somebody's searching Bank of America
they're probably not going to tap on an
ad for Chase Bank and so Apple doesn't
make money when somebody searches of
America and they show Chase because
people are looking for the Bank of
America because they bank at Bank of
America they're not searching Bank of
America cuz they're looking for a bank
they're looking for the app and so I
mean it's probably the exact opposite on
like SEO it's like you know if
somebody's searching Bank of America
online or like you know other kind of
keywords it might make more sense but on
the App Store specifically when
somebody's looking for a very specific
app Apple's not making money if people
are are having to scroll past the app so
yeah it makes a lot of sense so on brand
defense you just you you really
experiment and try and B as low as
possible to maintain as much impression
share as you're comfortable with to make
sure you're not kind of losing out on
the opportunities man I bet I mean that
advice alone you know I don't know how
how it does seem like a lot of companies
you know they just kind of throw money
at App Store sech CHS and don't operate
in a very sophisticated way um and of
course tons of them you know hire
Consultants or have internal people who
are really good or have agencies working
on it who know these kind of things
there's probably folks listening to this
podcast who who don't know that and and
aren't you know paying close enough
attention and you may have just saved
them like tens of thousands of dollars
just go in there and lower your bed and
watch impression chair I mean there's
one more thing about um the RO and case
studies and like one thing I noticed is
a lot of case studies don't mention if
it's generic or brand this brand usually
has highest ORS of any kind of if think
about it right like uh that's what we we
made the user come to App Store and
their highest intent possible um so when
we seeing the revenue R I would consider
brand as its own entity we treat it as
we do not compare brand with any other
high intent generary keywords or
computer keywords or like broad match
keywords I would treat it as two
different things I do not even mix up
the data as a an entire like apple
strategy yeah yeah that makes a lot of
sense yeah because if your overall Roi
looks amazing yes because you're
cannibalizing but if you can pay half
your Roi is going to look even better so
that's
great um we already kind of talked a
little bit about the the trend in CPAs
going up up up but I wanted to dig into
that a little bit so we kind of talked
about some of the the the high uh CPA
like Finance and health and fitness and
some of these categories that are going
high what what about like low CPA are
there some categories that like are
opportunities some some um Arbitrage
available in the App Store in in certain
categories yeah even with the high
competition categories like we can have
some
CPA we can improve CPA better by just
expanding High intent and low intent
keywords and bid accordingly for example
yoga I know yoga if someone is typing
Yoga Yoga is high intent for my app um
I'm talking about yoga because it's so
such a generic app so but I also know if
someone is doing PES or um some kind of
like maybe there a low intent they may
not be interested in my app but it's
still like some if someone is looking
for health and fitness and piles maybe
they're low intent but I won't be same
as I would bit for yoga so I classify
that as low intent that way you can
expand keywords a lot and also keywords
we can think of it as a it's very this
where the night and day difference of
performance can occur in apple search
ads if I'm choosing bad keywords like
have 10 keywords that are not relevant
to app and bidding $10 each um we're
going to have some troubles this is a
human thing right like we know much
better you can use AI CH GPT to have
some ideas but the final say should be
yours of okay we are using this this
keyword because it's low intent and
we'll bit lower and in hopes that uh we
get more sus and the best part about
Apple s is there are two types of
keywords exit is not 100% EXA but is
more like yoga
for uh woman for example is that if I'm
biding as exact keyword that's fine but
there's another keyword type called
broad match what it means is in any
variations can also we can all right
automat show up for me if yoga for women
is same intent as yoga for women in
30s I know it's a long uh Tale But yoga
for women I don't care what the
following Search terms are because I
already know yoga for women and these
keywords usually are dynamic because if
you look at the App Store App uh if you
type yoga you'll see apple suggest some
system and these change very often so
the competition would may not exist for
some of the ssts and that's a low
hanging fruit uh run the broad but bit
obviously bid lower I'm a big fan of
classifying keywords and bidding
different for each based on their group
like brand and regarding low it's also
very Dynamic even with the high
competition some keywords may not have
any competition at all and there's like
think of stock market there's like so so
many so many people trying to buy stocks
and we cannot predict what's going to
happen so this is where you know we try
to have as many as Rel keywords and we
expect some may go down in impression
share some may go up orall we just see
Improvement in performance so is that
how um broad match works I'm a little
naive here I have not unfortunately I
mean you and I were talking about like I
actually want to start running half
store search ads campaigns for my
weather app I've been holding off
because I'm like I don't know if they're
going to be profitable and like it is
tough in a category like weather and but
so I'm a little naive to exactly how all
of this works but maybe that's good
because I think a lot of the the folks
who listen to a podcast like this don't
necessarily like day in day out run
campaigns so it's helpful to kind of
Define some of these terms and describe
in a little more detail how some of this
works so broad match if if you do a
broad match for like yoga for women will
it broad match anything related to yoga
for women or or does it still have to
have like yoga and women in the search
terms like how how dangerous is it to
set a broad match will it just like pull
any random stuff in there there app yes
it just just because we said your yoga
for women it doesn't mean that Apple may
apple may show for totally unrelated if
it thinks that if Apple algorithm thinks
for example pelaton if Apple thinks
Pelon is related to yoga for our ad we
may be paying for pelaton keyboard but
the good thing is we can even track this
there's a the report called Search terms
report it's better to occasionally check
you know this report and make sure okay
all our spending is going to the right
kind of keywords usually the search
Terps is not perfect Apple only shows
search Terps if they're if you spend
enough and if you get enough Impressions
but that's fine that's what we want
anyway right we don't need like
thousands of Search terms report so then
in this case like if if you have a yoga
app and you see in the report that it's
bidding for pelaton and and it's a high
bid and you're not getting good at Roi
do do you go in there and then
specifically say don't bid on pelaton so
the good thing about that is we can
track which keyword is causing Pon to
causing or app to show for Pon usually I
just go in there and T it down to really
stupidly low that either we get really
really cheap like installs or app we
force Apple to notch or add I'm not a
big fan of removing keyboards too much
often um yeah these are Dynamic Trends
right let say I have a yoga for and
apple is showing pelaton search down for
this U for my app this week it doesn't
mean that it's going to keep doing that
forever right like maybe next month that
might be my most profitable keyword if I
just remove that keyword I just lost my
opportunity um forever but if I bit low
and I can re retry it later two three
months and see how is it performing um I
think yoga for is not a great example
for broad but you can think of a as uh
let's take weather since your app
hopefully I'm not giving away weather
app Secrets uh imagine we bding we just
don't know anything about Apple sear CHS
but we know our app is about weather so
you can run on weather as exact it means
that any variation weather like we show
the ad and we pay high for that let's
assume we did not do any keyword
research we don't have any keyword list
uh if you also bid on Broad of the same
so we are running two keywords basically
Apple may show weather map weather
information weather
alerts as far as we concerned those are
also relevant for for us right so and
you can go to the multiple levels like
Now weather alerts we can bid on weather
alerts because Apple showed Oh there's a
weather alerts keyword now the we do the
same thing we add weather alerts as
except and also Broad and our hope is
that if someone is searching for wether
alerts Philadelphia it still relevant
because Mac still relevant and if
someone is searching whether alerts Los
Angeles um same thing so that way like
you can that's why I'm I'm a big fan of
maintaining a relevant keybo list
because this is onetime action right
like once we add weather alerts we're
not going to unless the app changes
entire business model and the name and
the functionality it's really rare that
the keyword is going to be applicable
for work yeah that's a good point though
cuz like for my app it would actually be
the opposite so we would start with
weather as a broad match and we would
probably see that WEA alerts is a very
low intent keyword because we actually
don't have alerts in the app it's
something we actually want to add to the
app so then what you're saying is what
we would do then is put weather as broad
match when we see weather alerts come in
and it's um not creating a great Roi
even if maybe it is driving downloads
because people don't realize the app
doesn't do it but then they get into the
app it doesn't do it leave a bad review
they uh don't buy or they cancel the
free trial or whatever um so then we
make WEA alerts a exact match and then
we bid really low because maybe we still
get impressions and maybe we still make
some money but we want that specific
keyword to be super low price but then
when I add the feature then we already
have some relevancy for it and then I
can bump the bids back up right in this
case like when we are sure this a
particular keyword is really badly
performing and it's consist over and
over again he can actually add it as
negative keyword basically what we're
saying to Apple is anything that says
with alerts yeah take me out I'm not I'm
not in the game so that's actually much
better uh but we need to be absolutely
sure that this keyword is never going to
be a good fit um I noticed some um
advice that yeah just remove negative
any keywords that don't generate Rue in
first week that is really not great
strategy in my opinion because
everything is dynamic right like some
competitors may be biding high this week
they may a drop off tomorrow it's all
Dynamic that's why I'm a big fan of
Apple search it gives us a lot of data
to validate and test our
hypothesis yeah in this case if you know
this keyword is a bad news yeah we just
add it as negative keyword one time
thing and we never have to worry about
it again so is that is that how exact
and Broad match work so I I mean a lot a
lot of people who like work in in the
industry or constantly managing these
things will know that but I'm sure
there's a lot of folks listening who
don't and then honestly even the people
who work in this day and day out could
probably learn some of the intricacies
about how it does and doesn't work uh
from you as much as you've managed This
and like work with so many different
folks over the years so um so yeah how
how does broad match work yeah the goal
for us when you when we using broad
match is to Capt
like exponential number of Search terms
that are still relevant to our app and
added benefit is usually for these
keywords these are so dynamic they
change every week they may be low in
popularity um so they will our computors
may not be bidding really so so we've
talked a bit about fluctuation but one
of the biggest fluctuations is is
seasonality it's like you know I'm sure
January 1 all the Search terms related
to health and fitness are Bid to crazy
and and that's to be expected um but any
other things you think people should be
watching out for seasonality wise or or
how does that impact CPAs and and how
should you be preparing and structuring
your campaigns for seasonality so you
don't end up like you know paying too
much but also so you don't miss out on
the opportunities when there maybe are
high higher Roi searches when maybe you
are bidding lower even when there are
higher uh intent people coming in yeah I
mean for you us stor friend like the
Thanksgiving is the usually the highest
competitive space it's the same similar
phenomenon like a wave lifting up all
the VES kind of things so even if it's
nothing even if our app it has nothing
to do with shopping we may see our CPA
you know going up bit High even summer
time is like usually for like it depends
on kind of apps like from some
categories the summer is actually the
cheapest CPA for some reason you can
think of this as cool if I'm education
app and usually the best time period to
test any new app is I mean if you're if
someone is thinking of um trying out
Apple CHS is during February till summer
this is kind of a a kind of weirdly low
energy in the you know competition
competitive space um because the January
high is gone and now things are coming
back um but it depends on the app too
right like um if I'm if my app is
dealing with something with U for
example flights like flight tracker
obviously like um I can't benefit much
uh because there not Peak Travel season
um yeah those are the seasonality trends
and and some of them are
counterintuitive too like I was actually
talking to Ryan Jones from flighty
recently and he was saying how surprised
he was that holiday travel is such a
like you I thought I I I think the
conversation was related to me saying oh
you must do like really good business in
the summer he's like no actually like
the summer is fine but the holidays is
where people are like way higher intent
like traveling more care more about
delays and stuff like that and so some
of these like seasonal Trends are
probably counterintuitive and like even
you're running your app thinking oh you
know let's take all Trails for example
it's like oh well the summer is going to
be peak season Maybe but are there are
there ways that that you kind of I mean
pretty much you just need to be watching
week in week out are there but Are there
specific ways that you track these
campaigns to make sure that that you're
not missing out on either potentially
bidding lower kind of when when CPA
maybe drift lower or bidding higher when
there's actually higher intent people
coming in how how do you manage that on
a day and day out basis it depends on
the like how our app category how the
competition is um for some apps like it
depends on what our competitors are
doing because when I'm saying
competitors I'm not talking about exact
clu competitors I'm talking about any
app that are bidding heavily and for a
long time for our primary keywords High
intent keywords it depends on that for
day in day out usually we should not we
just keep in mind that hey this is
expected and we can look over the good
thing is it should correlate with
Organic traffic as well so we can just
come back to AB connect and check last 2
years what's our Trend and we can expect
similar um in apple SE I'm not a big fan
of changing bits by the seasonality
because uh like I said it's like stock
market right it's everything is dynamic
we cannot predict that we'll get
impression share of this keyword but we
can see the results and act on it I mean
there a best thing about data right like
we don't have to make any assumptions we
can see the data and act accordingly so
so what you're saying is a better the
better tactic is just to watch the
keywords and so if you're getting a
higher Roi on a specific keyword no
matter the seasonality that's when you
would experiment with increasing the bid
and then when if you see Roi drop then
that's when you experiment with lowering
the bid and you kind of like you you
should just be doing this as like
standard practice anyway not necessarily
focused on the seasonality when I say
watch keywords means um it's like
conscient process right like um imagine
I'm running an apple Church campaigns
for for my company and I just go in
every day every week once in a while and
I just be according to what I'm seeing
it doesn't matter maybe Germany is the
least performing campaign it doesn't
matter what season right I just yeah you
know what I'm not going to spend too
much budget so let me bit lower for the
entire ad group maybe um us is least
performing but Germany's best performing
in December for some reason I don't know
because these are all external factors
we cannot analyze like why it happened
we can just react what we're seeing
based on like past 15 days or past 7
days so and and speaking of Roi H how do
you think about Roi because you know
you're you're not always going to be
able to get I mean the ma the magic is
like a plug in a keyword and like 150%
Roi in seven days and then you spend a
million dollars a month and you're just
making money hand and foot but that's
not how it actually works in the real
world but so how how do you first
measure Roi
and then how do you think about
Roi yeah um imagine um I'll take we'll
take an example of a a regular generic
app with 7day free trial and some let's
talk about my app so if I start running
because I am going to start running
weather uh uh App Store search ads on
different weather terms and so I'll and
I'll probably be talking about this over
time on the podcast of like you know
what's worked and what hasn't for me so
yeah a weather app so I start running
ads for my weather app so we'll use that
as hypothetical what is the free trial
is there a free trial 7even days 7 Days
perfect here's the thing about Revenue
in apple SE ads Apple search ads by
default doesn't give Revenue uh doesn't
show Revenue like unlike meta you know
uh Google
ads but there's some ways that you can
use mmps um like other platforms and get
the information and Link it up and
revenue cat yes yeah Reven does a great
job like linking up keywords and um ad
groups and you can use that information
to analyze my recommendation is like um
do not go in there expecting a hard
number as Revenue goal and if it doesn't
hit uh take the entire Channel down
because these are really Dynamic and
there are so many things that we can
improve on um for example like if you
it's it's totally different of Revenue
if you if I Google right now what is a
good R the usual wisdom is 4 400%
what they mean is like okay if you spend
$100 you need you expect $400 coming
back but that is uh not for app um there
not that wisdom is not for app marketing
because for simple reason we have
subscriptions right like we and also all
this uh 400% R is golden metric is for
like for example if I'm selling T-shirts
yeah there's a metric I can follow on
but because if I'm a person who buys my
t-shirt will never buy the same t-shirt
next month um but app there's a
important metric called time
to break even what it means is it's fine
even if you don't get 100% RS in the
first week I mean obviously if you get
that that's good but even if you get
like 40% or 50% ORS it's actually not
bad result because we can still improve
on add more keywords we can fine tune
and also
there is a we can check our LTV right
and because we're bidding for high
intent we know that these users are
perfect users of our app so we can
expect we can improve the in app like
experience to make sure they don't turn
and they if you have monthly
subscription hopefully because if you
think about it cohorted or mean we only
spend that let's say we spend $3 for
that install for that user who started
this free trial
and they did convert in that case we
only spent $3 one time for that user and
that's it but the revenue is like
hopefully our app is better and like not
like this not huge turn we can keep on
the revenues keep coming in so um
there's a time delay we just have to
keep track of it um and so then every
app developer has to kind of decide from
a cash flow perspective from a long-term
business perspective I mean I was
talking to one person who
you know because you you hear so much in
the industry of like oh you know what's
your 7-Day Ras what's your 30-day row
you know are you getting row positive in
90 days like what's a metric and I was
talking to somebody who has like really
great organic traffic so their their
business is just spinning off cash and
so their metric was 365 day rows so
their their metric was can I
spend today and at least get to 100% by
the first annual renewal and for a lot
of businesses that can make sense like
if the cash flow makes sense if you're
wanting to like really grow and then the
cool thing like you're were saying is
like those people who renewed that first
year you get to Raz positive in 365 days
which again it's crazy it's hard to
float that if if you know for a lot of
companies but then like a bunch of those
people are going to new the next year
and the next year after that and so it's
an Arbitrage opportunity to grow faster
now if you have the cash and you have
some level of confidence in those
renewals um that you're going to start
stacking those cohorts sooner and sooner
that that's actually why I want to start
advertising for my weather op as soon as
possible and I'm kind of kicking myself
for not starting is I should at least be
H picking up the lwh hanging fruit and
maybe this is kind of the message for
those of you who aren't currently doing
it and even for those of you who are and
maybe could even spend more than you
currently are is that I mean this is
Magic of the subscription app um model
is that that LTV is not capped even if
you have a average LTV for most apps who
are reasonably retentive whatever
average you calculate today is likely to
just keep going up o year after year
after year after year uh I mean I was
looking at my own app and seven years in
I still have 20% of people who
subscribed within the first month so
seven years still have 20% of people and
so if I can stack more of those cohorts
Now versus stacking them later even if
I'm not getting 100% Ras on day seven if
I can afford the cash to do that and
expand the business it's going to pay
dividends in the long run but you just
got to make sure you you have some level
of retention and confidence in that and
then you have the cash and the risk
tolerance to go ahead and invest more
heavily yeah obviously the the C is that
we have all the basics uh sort out what
I mean is the install to free trial
ratio the free trial to conversion ratio
but this is nothing to do with apple SS
right um the goal of Apple SS is bring
in new users uh we have to like uh
improve those inapp conversion rates
anyway ourselves um regardless if you
run ASA or not and one more thing about
Ros is Ros should not be the primary
metric um it should be combination of
Revenue and rs for example we can think
of two apps let's take meditation let's
take hits space and Comm these are
imaginary numbers um so don't sue me
imagine hits space and and Comm both are
running Apple CHS and headspace is
spending let's say uh a million dollars
and their their R is 75% RS but Comm is
spending $2 million
with 65% RS on the paper it looks like
head space is doing much better right
like um because it's getting 70% within
like first 30 days or whatever but in
long term the Comm is actually very
positioned to lead because at the end of
the one year they both are going to have
100% RS anyway according to their LTV
metrics but Comm generated double the
amount of Revenue that headspace even
though there's a RS is not great for the
com app so it is a combination of
Revenue and R and if we don't consider
Revenue our competitor will and they
will eventually like bid higher of
whatever the RS we're getting currently
is going to suffer because now they're
going to bid higher for the our positive
RS keywords so yeah revenue is the one
of the major number as well because the
sport we want right like well and the
other thing that Revenue takes into
account that you that's hard to factor
in is that there is some organic lift
when you're running ASO I know this is
another kind of controversial topic and
uh I know you have some high hypothesis
around the impact but the the reality is
there's some impact um whether your
hypothesis is correct or you know tons
of people in Industry are like oh it's
going to be magic like run as ASA and
then your ASO is going to be amazing but
so what what's your hypothesis on the
impact of Asa on ASO I would call it
conspiracy theory I would not even call
hypothesis because that's such a take it
with grain of bucket with bucket of salt
this is why I love having you on versus
like a growth hacker cuz a growth hacker
would have just been like oh yeah 100%
this is how it works you're like you see
the data day in and day out you're like
this is even a hypothesis because you
want to have a level of confidence in in
the answer but yeah what do you think
because honestly you probably you your
conspiracy theory is probably better
than a lot of folks who speak
confidently about this my theory is that
download Volume correlates with Organic
ranking it's one of those Trend that it
doesn't matter what app it's always
correlates with a such a strong
efficiency the second factor I think is
this is where the conspiracy theory part
come in even at the keyword level
imagine we have we are having same
amount of downloads there's not much
huge change in the download volume but
you start running for weather app Apple
search ads let's say whether radar maybe
is one of the feature of your app yep
that's a great keyword for my app yeah
so whether radar you imagine your
current organic ranking is maybe Sony or
something as soon as you start running
Apple search for that particular weather
radar system and our app generate some
installs you may see the organic ranking
go really high maybe even reaching top
10 or top 20 just the skyrocketing
within but the download Volume is same
that's my conspiracy theory that maybe
App Store considers Apple search as
keyword as part of App Store um and now
even the App Store algorithm can see
that oh you know what this weather app
is totally relevant to weather radar
because users are clicking on it and
using it um and don't why but then why
wouldn't it change the download Volume
if you go from like if if I start
advertising for weather radar and I go
get go from I'm probably like 200 in
that search currently so I go from 200
to 20 um why would download Volume not
change I'm only talking about that
particular keyboard it's an imaginary
hypothesis that we are running Apple
search for only that keyword let's
assume our um daily download is like 100
units in us and we started running that
keyword for two installs a day I'm
giving an example maybe at the end of
the week the download Volume is not that
high like 100 versus 102 installs but
the organic ranking for every other
keyword May remain same but for this
particular keyword what we running in
haet chats we may may see a kind of
organic ranking uplift but like I said
take it B bucket of salt it may not
happen I don't recommend spending a lot
of budget just for that purpose because
it may happen it may not happen and yeah
it does seem like Apple's search
algorithm although it's still
frustrating it doesn't feel like that
still especially great at it um but it
does seem like it's gotten more more
sophisticated over the years so the
people who who think there's going to be
a onetoone response in taking us certain
action might be surprised and like you
said yeah it's it's a lot of money to
put on the line with when any kind of
algorithm like this there's no not a a
level of certainty on it while we are on
the topic the downar volume ARG going
rank uh the theory is that it is kind of
like a chicken and egg issue for
especially for new apps or apps that are
actually best in the class better than
all the competitors but the competitors
will be always number one in that case
do not treat Apple as a like a there's a
channel we should never run on because
this may be the better option because as
long as your app is better than
competitors and they're ranking number
one even then you can actually get high
intent as long as we talked about the
basic arap conversion ratios are basic
um this these all great if that's the
case like you don't even need like to
run um million install campaigns you can
just Target those High intent we're not
going to get quantity um but we'll get
the quality users and as long as we
scaling up a revenue why does it matter
how much if you're ranking number one or
not I'm talking about apple J obviously
it matters that we rank number one but
sometimes it's nextra impossible for
some keywords we can never rank number
one right yeah I know that makes sense
and speaking of scaling that's actually
something I wanted to talk to you about
um and that that's kind of the the
challenge with App Store search ads is
that even though it can be an incredible
source of really high intent downloads
the the kind of what everybody in the
industry talks about is like well that's
great but it's not scalable so how how
do you think about scalability in app
store search ads scalability I mean
obviously it can we cannot compare Apple
SS with meta campaigns or Tik Tok
campaigns because it's um it's Apple
verus ores um we are looking quality
versus quantity um in my opinion the
best way to scale is to adding more
keywords High intent low intent like
segmented by it um and adding broad
match keywords that will literally like
be exponentially increasing your um
awareness and more countries by default
um that's a easy way to
scale and just monitor campaigns and
emplo some kind of u a workflow like
campaign structure should be in a such a
way that it's easy to maintain them I'm
not a big fan of like creating hundreds
of campaigns for one country um because
you only have one competitor set of
keywords right like we cannot have
multiple competitors um we don't need to
run different different ad groups um
yeah the bottom line is adding more
keywords relevant keywords the more
relevant the better they are um and
adding more there's always competitor
share that we can improve and brand is
thing as we talked about it is its own
thing we do not consider brand as our uh
because brand is kind of steady flow
right like I mean it's a good thing the
brand Impressions go up but that's how I
scale yeah but then what are what are
the Ian do you see I guess it's just
going to be so contextual right it's
like for a health and fitness app it's
like if they're willing to spend the
money it can be a massive Channel
because there's ton of high intent
people coming and searching relevant
keywords but then if you're in a niche a
really small Niche where like you're
really only relevant to very small
number of searches then you're going to
hit the wall sooner right so it's just
it's just very contextual of like when
you're going to hit the wall but then
you don't know that that you've really
hit the wall until you've done the
experiments with broad match and
experimented with the bidding and like
tried stuff right yeah and apple is one
of those things where the competitors
are kind of can dictate what we can do
next for example imagine there's a
weather app and imagine there's for some
weird reason there's no weather app in
apple searchs ever running Apple
searchs uh your app is the only one that
has Apple Sears in that case your CPA
will be like probably in cense in us
your R can Skyrocket but that's like a
dream scenario but imagine you like you
have like 25 weather competitors weather
app competitors in United States
unfortunately it means that for the same
number of installs your CPA probably
like is 10 times now but the good thing
is competitors also Dynamic just because
they're bidding for a keyword doesn't
mean that Apple considers them relevant
same phenomenal brand as well if you're
your competitor running same witha radar
keyword and for some reason your app is
performing better and apple can see that
even if you're beaing half of your
computer Apple will still prefer your ad
guess Apple has to make money too right
like they can just show the other app if
it's not getting too much of uh traction
yeah yeah that's interesting and then
and so then part part of what you're
saying is like even even if you are
super Niche and you're like oh it's
going to it's going to tap me out really
quick go get those keywords because
they're going to be so cheap so if
you're if you're at a niche and you're
not running Apple search ads you're
probably leaving money on the table
because there probably are some high
intent low traffic keywords that still
you're just printing money if you can
pick those up yeah the we just need to
adjust our expectations like we can't
have like a million dollar day one you
know Meta Meta kind of you know Blitz
but if it have our expectations set and
yeah and the interesting thing too is
like even though meta you can
theoretically scale even for for a niche
app like you'll saturate that kind of
Ideal customer profile and so yeah you
can Scale near infinite on meta but you
might not Scale profitably near infinite
because is similar like as you start
bidding higher and as you start
saturating your market and those High
intent users that you're going to be
able to to get to then your cost ER are
going to go up too because now you're
now you're ending up with medium intent
people and then low intent people so
like nothing's truly infinitely scalable
unless you're I mean like I guess these
like T teu and stuff like that like when
anybody is truly a potential customer
there are like you can't scale to a
level that that a lot of app can't but
most apps aren't that so and one of the
interesting thing is that how ad
channels can behave differently for the
same app obviously there any mature app
company will be using multiple ad
channels at the same time meta and apple
searches and Google whatnot the
difference is that Apple SES is
relatively easier channel to maintain
the reason is we don't have to create
this influencer videos make it quirky
like and there's a thing called fittig
imagine you probably notice is that if
you're using Instagram and US seeing
same ad every day like it it it
something will sit in and will never
it's actually create May create a
version to the app um but Apple
Searchers we don't have that problem
right because we're targeting new user
looking exactly for that keyword so the
ad fitting is not a really huge thing
there is some display formats like
search tabs or to dat tabs they but it's
not like that extent of Instagram where
we see like u
10 ads of the same app in the row and
it's not that great experience and it's
easier to scale because we're not
dealing with creatives apple such as
creatives is our whatever the
screenshots we have metad right so and
the keywords we don't change keywords
right like it's always the same keywords
we may add it we may I mean we may pause
them or we may bit lower but a weather
radar until the your app exist in the
App Store the weather rad or is always
be relevant we don't need to think
creatively and it's great for people
like us uh who are developers because we
don't have to worry about like creative
videos that you know catch people's
attention yeah speaking of of creative
and appstor screenshots and stuff though
um how has product pages and being able
to send specific keywords to specific
product pages started to change the game
because you you there is a a certain
level now where you can experiment a
little more with you know quote unquote
creative on the App Store because you
can create a separate product page for
these different kind of use cases um
have you seen that help accounts you
know scale and get to better robots
those are good problems to have because
if you're considering a keyword specific
custom prodct Pages it means that we
already maximized whatever the
impression share and we are reaching
let's assume like there's a shopping app
and they maximized 80% of impression sh
for all generic terms um where custom
product pages can move the needle is
let's assume there is a Tim is running a
ad for Thanksgiving and it's like a
monthlong feature right but timu wants
it Thanksgiving in the title and
subtitle and screenshots but they can
create its entire custom product page
just for Thanksgiving and have
Thanksgiving all across only for United
States and they can use it um to scale
up those Thanksgiving people who are
creating why I'm saying Thanksgiving it
should be Black Friday right Black
Friday DS and yeah that way like you
know Timo can scale up those keywords
and in a indirect way I have also like
custom product pages for AB testing this
a one easy way to like simply Implement
AB testing let see and you can even use
similar uh Search terms like for example
bid for have the United States states
for our default product page and use
utilize the new custom product page we
want to test and see which one performs
better and just compare each um there
shouldn't be much difference between
East Coast and West Coast anyway or you
can also try ad scheduling which means
during the first half of the day you can
use it but I'm not a big fan because the
day time of the day May dictate for
example like if I'm if I'm a yoga app I
may be look in the morning right so um
so the geographical separation might be
a good place to test yeah interesting
all right well it's been so fun chatting
today but we do need to to wrap up as as
we do is there anything else you want to
share or or anything you want to to tell
the audience yeah um for new apps uh use
apple SS as kind of customer Discovery
thing and you can I mean you don't have
to spend daily purges like like hundreds
of dollars you can even get 5 six
installs a day spending $10 $20 but use
that as high intent and use them as a
because you want to Target high intent
users and improve your app and check
this out our platform is designed to
scale Apple suggest profitably SC
searchat optimization.com um and find me
on LinkedIn and ask me any questions and
I'm always happy to talk about Apple
search chats awesome and as I've kind of
been wrapping up these podcasts too um
if you have specific questions instead
of hitting them up on LinkedIn where
only the two of you can talk uh feel
free to do it on uh on the sub Club
community so we'll we'll po post this
podcast on subcl Club Community um you
can respond to that or just just tag
dilip um so that your questions can be
um beneficial to the the rest of the
community as well yeah I I I was
checking out your uh company and it and
again it's really cool that you started
this from a data
perspective um and and you know it's
it's clear that you've you know built
these the algorithms to to make it so
much easier for folks to um to do a lot
of things that we talked about today um
to manage those bids to uh automate some
of that as well um so yeah it looks like
a really cool platform and uh something
I'm going to be checking out myself yeah
sounds great awesome thanks for joining
me and thanks for sharing all these
great nuggets with
folks thanks so much for listening if
you have a minute please leave a review
in your favorite podcast player you can
also stop by chat. subclub docomo our
private community
[Music]